<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certain proposalls in order to the peoples freedome and accommodation in some particulars with the advancement of trade and navigation of this commonwealth in generall ... / by Henry Robinson.</title>
            <author>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57436</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1670</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22464</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12489055</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12489055</idno>
            <idno type="VID">62329</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57436)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 62329)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 290:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certain proposalls in order to the peoples freedome and accommodation in some particulars with the advancement of trade and navigation of this commonwealth in generall ... / by Henry Robinson.</title>
                  <author>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M. Simmons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Only such portions of this tract as bear on the questions of exchanges and of English monetary history are here reprinted.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 27.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Folger Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Balance of trade --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Bills of exchange.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:62329:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:62329:1"/>
            <p>CERTAIN PROPOSALLS In order to the Peoples Freedome and Accommodation in ſome Particulars.</p>
            <p>With the Advancement of Trade and Navigation of this Common-Wealth in generall.</p>
            <p>Humbly tendered to the view of this proſperous Parliament, in this Juncture of time, wherein They may both with more ſafety and farre better deliberation judge thereof, and if they ſee requiſit, put them in a way of ſpeedy execution, to the great enriching, ſecuring, cementing, and contenting the Univerſality of this Nation, which hath been much deſired, and ſhall be ſtill endeavou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d by <hi>Henry Robinſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> Printed by <hi>M. Simmons,</hi> in <hi>Alderſgate-ſtreete</hi> next doore to the <hi>Golden Lyon.</hi> 1652.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:62329:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:62329:2"/>
            <head>To the Supreme Authority of this NATION, <hi>The High Court of Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot ſay I now preſent You with much more than what I have formerly either in Print or Manuſcript preſſed upon ſeverall Members of Parliament, which perhaps were taken, as I obſerve They receive every morning of courſe as They paſs into the Houſe, other mens Papers, Petitions, Books, which, through the preſent buſineſſe They are then to fall upon, many of Them may be neceſſitated to put into their Pockets, without ſo much as examining the Title, much leſſe peruſing them afterwards.</p>
            <p>However I am induced to take this farther paines, in breifly recapitulating onely the heads thereof, and varying their dreſs, with ſomewhat more exaggerating their neceſſity for this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions wellfare, and Your own honour and concernment, to ſee them put in ſpeedy execution; Expecting to finde You now not only better at leiſure to give eare thereto, but even ſeeking out all manner of oportunities for Imploying the Remaynder of this Parliament, about ſuch Affaires as may yet ſurpaſs, and ſerve as a Crown to all Your former glorious Acheivements of warre, to wit, the putting and eſtabliſhing Us in the wayes of Peace, which cannot be done without confounding the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiction of Courts of Common Law and Equity, and reducing them into one kinde, at leaſt, mixt both of Common Law and Equity; The Reformation of many irrationall and deſtructive Lawes, ſupplying new ones in their ſtead; But eſpecially by blaſting the preſent expenſive delatory and corrupt manner of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:62329:3"/>
proceedings in all Courts, particularly that of Chauncery, both endleſs and boundleſs; all which doe eminently favour the Rich againſt the Poore; ſuch as are ſtrong in freindſhip againſt the Fatherles and widowes; even the Juſt againſt the Innocent, and Right againſt Wrong, ſo certainly, as that whenſoever the Poore, Fatherles and Widow, Freindles and Innocent happen to be ſued for any thing this world affords them, could they but ſo much deny themſelves, and theſe worldly ſuperfluities, it were far better for them, according to that Goſpel advice, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 40. to renounce them, than wage a ſuit at Law, though at laſt they were ſure to get the victory, in regard if it be rightly eſtimated, it cannot countervaile the loſs of time, expence of money, and the vexatiouſneſs of ſo many years ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciting and attendance: But I ſhall take occaſion to inſiſt hereon more largely another time; and at preſent cheifly preſent You with ſeverall particulars, in order to the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the People in their freedoms, and ſetting the wheeles of Trade a running; Some whereof are of imminent neceſſity, and without which, theſe three Nations cannot ſo ſpeedily at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to ſuch a competent eſtate of Riches and accommodati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as either to live ſecured from Forreign Powers, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly amongſt themſelves.</p>
            <p>It is not the bare name of <hi>Libertie,</hi> and of a <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> or <hi>Free-State,</hi> can long ſatisfie the People, much leſs content, or really make them happy: Some forme of Government is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, but all Formes are good, though one more perfect and better than another; And doubtleſs, it may be ſafely affirmed, that even the worſt kinde of Government is capable of being ſo managed, or ordered, as that a People might enjoy better dayes under it, than ever any yet did under the very beſt of Governments from the beginning of the world; So lgnorant have moſt former Governours and Powers been; I rather chooſe to Impute their errours to their Ignorance, becauſe I conceive it may be found upon debate, that no ſort of People have been more Ignorant of their own Charge and Duty, and more to ſeek in their reſpective Stations and Callings, than Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, or the Powers of what kinde ſoever, eſpecially Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall or Imperiall Powers; and yet what Ranck of Mankind have ſo great advantage, or can deſcharge their truſt, I mean ſo far forth as the People would reſt ſatisfied therewith, with ſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:62329:3"/>
much eaſe as they, If they were not more Ignorant of their own Condition, their Myſterie and Trade, than other men? Poore People, Subjects as they are called and made throughout the world, are even become contented to beare with ſmall oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and cannot eaſily be provoked to attempt the wreſting the ſword out of a Tyrants hand; they are eaſily prevailed to ſubmit unto the ſtrongeſt ſword, ſo they may but enjoy the Liberty of their Conſciences, the Freedom of their perſons, and what they moyl and toyl for: Now, how eaſily may the Powers in being, of any Country at Peace, ſee this accompliſhed? And this being done, improve, encreaſe, and multiply their own Revenue, even to what extent they themſelves pleaſe, without aggrieving of the Subject, if They that take upon them to be Maſters of the World, did but underſtand the World a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right: If a ſingle man that hath 10000. l. in his purſe, muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be a weak man, or finde out wayes to maintaine himſelfe in an honorable Poſture, and encreaſe his ſtock beſides; with how much more advantage may a Prince, or the Powers in what Land ſoever that have a yearely Revennue of 100000. <hi>l.</hi> or of a million, doe the ſame? The late King had raiſed his yearly Revenue almoſt unto a million; and it is ſaid his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition as then aſpired no higher than the compleating it to a million: Now this Revenue of his, though it had yet been leſs, had his expences been managed with frugality, and the advance at years end been improved with dexterity, I will be bold to ſay, it might have put him into ſuch a capacity, as that at one twenty or thirty yeares end, he might not onely have bid defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to all this Nations enemies, even the King of <hi>Spain</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, but have reduced him to his own conditions, though that Kings yearly Revenue was then neer ten times as much, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt Maſter of all the gold and ſilver which from yeare to yeare keepes all Chriſtendome together by the ears.</p>
            <p>It is not ſo much the tranſcendent wiſdome and abilities of any Prince or Powers that gives them ſo great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage over others, as ſuch other reſpective Prince or Powers groſſe Ignorance or Weakneſſe which expoſes them there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto; and I beleive it will be granted me, that Princes and Common-wealths, in the game they play amongſt themſelves, doe commit more over-ſights, and thoſe groſſer too, then private perſons, for this cauſe only, in that private perſons,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:62329:4"/>
as their buſines is far leſſe, ſo they can better fathome and looke after it; Whereas Princes, for the moſt part, think no care ſo well becomming them, as that of their Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Paſstimes: And the Miniſters of Common-wealths many times, are ſo intent after their owne private affairs, and that under colour, and in a pretended purſuance of the Publick; or elſe if it cannot be made gainſome to them, ſhift it off from one to another until in the upſhot (according to our own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Every mans buſines, no mans huſines</hi>) it happen to be neglected by them al: To prevent which great miſcheif from endangering this hapily begun Common-wealth, I ſhould crave leave to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, that as there were in all times &amp; Countries, allowed ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Revenues, unto Kings and Princes that took the burthen of Government upon them, for the maintaining of their charge; So, if the ſame courſe be not taken with all Officers and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of a Common-wealth, that they may have a full mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance allowed them, they muſt either be found to neglect their owne Families, whilſt they ſtudy and follow after the Publick Affaires, which they will neither long have Joy in, nor be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted wiſe men for ſo doing; or ſeek themſelves, not only to the ſcandall, but perhaps even to the endangering of the Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>I would not be miſtaken, as though my Judgement were, that Members of future Parliaments or Repreſentatives, which I hope will be able to diſpatch all the buſineſſe that is proper to them in ſome few moneths, ſhould be thus provided for by Sallaries; but abſolutely on the contrary, whereby they may not have the temptation of coveting the Imployment.</p>
            <p>I may not here omit to make mention of Your great Wiſdom and Integrity, in paſſing thoſe ſelfe-denying Votes, of reſolving to put the Powers formerly committed to ſundry Parliament Committees, about matters for the moſt part totally below You, and exentrick, into the hands of ſuch as are no Members of Parliament, which otherwiſe would not only have growne to be an occaſion of great offence unto the People, but have abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely diſappointed the maine end of Parliaments, through want of leiſure to doe ſuch things, and tranſact ſuch buſineſſes only as cannot be done by any leſſe or Inferiour Authority, then of Your ſelves Aſſembled in Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:62329:4"/>Be pleaſed therefore for the better direction of future Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentatives, in convenient time to conſider and declare Your Judgements what work is peculiar for Parliaments, and what not, and accordingly become a Preſident, though You cannot become a Law unto Them.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed to conſider, whether all Petitioners, or even a Boy or Meſſenger in their behalfe, ought not to be admitted, and that as they come to Your door in courſe, and in like courſe be diſpatched ſpeedily with a ſhort anſwer endorſed upon their Petition, that they may know which way to ſteare, and what to truſt to: Alſo whether the like freedome for all perſons to Petition the Councell of State, be not neceſſary at alltimes; as alſo for audience to be given, ſo many dayes in a Week, to any perſon whatſoever, comming at ſuch houres as ſhall be agreed upon and publiſhed: So much the rather, that by this means many Addreſſes unto future Parliaments will be prevented, which is to be endeavoured by all means poſſible. The great ſtate and diſtance which hath continually been kept betweene the Rulers and the People, in times of Tiranny and Ignorance, wherein poore Suppliants could not be admitted or heard, how equitable ſoever their Supplications were, without the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of ſome State-favourite or other, doubtleſſe over-ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the poore hood-winked Papiſts to make ſo many Mediators in Heaven: O let not this Hopefull Common-wealth, run the hazard of being blaſted for not better guarding us from this Idolatry, or ſuffer us to languiſh any longer in the like ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, wherein it hath been almoſt impoſſible for any one to get a Petition to be read either in Parliament or Counſell of State, unleſſe he had a Saint there to befriend him, who if he were not both very eminent and zealous, would likely either refuſe to promote it, or not prevaile to get it granted, though perhaps it ought to have been done of courſe. But for Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and in the Intervalls, for ſuch in whom the chiefe Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer reſides, to ſhut up their doors and ears from receiving Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, and granting audience to all Commers, is a ſymptom of the moſt deſperate Lethargy in the Powers, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of ſudden Innovation and miſery to the Nation.</p>
            <p>Nay I will goe one degree higher, and aſſert, that it is far leſſe miſcheivous to indulg a Liberty of Libelling, then to deny the freedome of Petitioning and ſpeaking truth; though indeed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:62329:5"/>
that which ſome Perſons and thoſe in Powers too, ſometimes terme libelling, may prove too ſad and reall truths; This Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hath encountred much there of whithin theſe twelve yeares; And yet it ought to be as ingeniouſly acknowledged, that even our Createſt Deliverers have been as highly ſlandered; But what are they the worſe for it? Hath it not added to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne? And they become ſo much more glorious Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours of their owne Paſſions, whilſt they continued doing good for ſuch as required them with evill? Whereas if the Liberty both of Speech and Printing had been reſtrained, under pretext of preventing libelling, we had to this day been continued in that deep ignorance and ſuperſtition, which together with our Predeceſſors we were borne in, never have been freed from Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny, nor exempted from Taxes of all ſorts, as ſhortly we may expect to be: The Citizens of <hi>Rome,</hi> even in theſe latter Centuries did ſo highly value this Liberty of ſpeaking their minds, as that they would not be baſſled out of it by their Popes Spiritualls nor Temporalls; Witneſſe that weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beaten mainſed ſtatue of <hi>Paſquin,</hi> which they Fiſhed up againe from the bottome of the River <hi>Tyber,</hi> and placed it where now it ſtil is to be ſeen, a moſt conſtant Avoucher &amp; Abettor of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they are forced to Publiſh in the Streets, becauſe it will not be admitted in the Court.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed then to Proclaime an abſolute Liberty of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, with a Toleration of all differing opinions, provided they reproach not one another, much leſſe thoſe formes which ſhall be chiefly countenanced by Authority: Let not the Aſſembly prevaile with their Bug-beare words of Hereſie or Blaſphemy, thereby tranſporting You to act beyond Your owne Reaſon or Underſtanding, untill they can tell You the difference between blaſpheming God, and the King, and what is meant by blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the King, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21. 10. Or Infallibly demonſtrate this or that which they aſſert for Hereſie to be ſo.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed to take away the ſcandall and temptation from the Goſpel-Miniſtry, not only of being Tyth-coveters, but of perſecuting and Impleading People for their Tyths ſake, which even the Jewes to whom only they were due, and they only of the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> and that <hi>Canaan</hi> only, were never warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> nor did any of them ever practiſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then receiving them from ſuch as paid them voluntari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:62329:5"/>
except the Sonnes of <hi>Eli,</hi> who for that cauſe were called the <hi>Sonnes of Belial,</hi> as You may ſee 1 <hi>Sam. ch.</hi> 2. from verſ. 8. to the 17. Eaſe many of the beſt of People of this Nation by diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting that Ordinance for <hi>Treble damages</hi> for refuſing pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they doe moſt conſcientiouſly and ſincerely: The work would neither be difficult nor chargeable: Pleaſe only to Enact all Tythes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> payable at preſent to the Miniſtry, to be paid unto Officers of the Common-wealth, and that the Common-wealth allow a competent maintenance to all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Preaching Miniſters, whether in Parochiall or private Aſſemblies, as hath been for many years, and is ſtill practiſed by the Provinciall, States of <hi>Holland,</hi> even towards the Engliſh both of the Presbyterian, and Congregationall or Independent way at <hi>Amſterdam:</hi> But this is not all, the Inequality of Tyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both of the Miniſter and Impropriator is deſtructive to Husbandry, and occaſions that Bread-Corne is continually ſo ſcarce and dear amongſt us: to prevent which, It may likely be found expedient, that ſuch lands as are plowed be rated by the acre, and rather pay leſſe then other land, in regard of the great charge and conſequently hazzard the Husband-man is at in plowing of them up, whereby he may be encouraged to plow greater quantity then formerly.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed to declare our freedome from being compelled to any manner of Oathes of Covenanting Engagements, which, as Light and Liberty burſt out amongſt us, doe daily more and more diſcover, not only the unneceſſarineſſe thereof, but even the Evil and Entanglements, into which they brought us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoydably through the Peoples differing Judgements and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, each one interpreting them (and that rightly too) in their owne ſenſe, whereby they think themſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to perſecute and oppoſe one another, who before lived lovingly in Peace, and might have ſtill continued ſo, had they not been joyntly engaged by Oath, which it was impoſſible for them all explicitly to underſtand alike, and conſequently muſt find themſelves bound to fall out and quarrell, even for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and their Oathes ſake.</p>
            <p>In the next place be pleaſed to caſt your thoughts on what is to be enacted for the Recovery and Advancement of Trade; The Councell of Trade are ſayd to have prepared ſeverall Bills in order thereunto; and it is high time that not only all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:62329:6"/>
of obſtructions be removed, but alſo that all manner of Advantages be ſearched out and made uſe of before it be too late.</p>
            <p>The firſt great preheminence which (amongſt Forraigne Nations) the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and ſome others of the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces have of us, is, In that their Inhabitants live together in Townes and Cities of indifferent magnitudes, neither too lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, nor too big, whereby they are enabled to accommodate and help themſelves to the beſt advantage, without making Proviſions, as to Food or Trading over dear.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is, in that ſo many of their ſaid Townes and Citties, either lye Scituated by the Sea-ſide, or have Navigable Rivers or Ditches from one unto another, and ſo into the Sea, by which meanes they have not onely all manner of Victualls brought ſo much cheaper unto them, but alſo all manner of Raw or unwrought Commodities, whereby their People are ſet a work, and by this meanes can afford all ſorts of Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, and Artificers work, ſo much cheaper as is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene Land and Water carriage.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they have moſt of their firſt materialls for building and rigging Ships cheaper; man them with fewer perſons, and Victuall them with courſer fare, and at cheaper rates, by which meanes they can carry all manner of bulkie Commodities (the ſraight whereof riſes high) ſo much cheaper, as muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily beat us out of all Markets, where they have a deſire to doe it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they alwayes have great ſtore of moneyes, even whatſoever ſummes can be deſired upon good ſecurity at Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt for four or five in the hundred.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, They have in a manner the whole Fiſhing Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as it were engroſſed unto themſelves, I mean thoſe of the United Provinces, but chiefly the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and <hi>Zealanders,</hi> which with Butter, Cheeſe, Rootes, (for little Fleſh ſerves their turnes) does not onely fully victuall themſelves, byt are by them exported into other Countryes in ſuch great aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, as that the whole Trade of thoſe Provinces is but the Return of their Fiſherie, ſo manifoldly complicated, as that it far exceeds, and is of far greater concernment to them, than all the Trade of theſe three Nations.</p>
            <p>To countermaund which, wee have no other remedy, but to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:62329:6"/>
fly to their own weapons, untill better preſent, and that is,</p>
            <p>1. To make all Rivers Naviagable as much as may be, and cut havigable Ditches in all places where the ground and ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutation will permit, and where there are no Rivers neer unto the Towns already built, nor poſſibility of cutting Navigable Ditches; it will be neceſſary to ſee where ſuch Navigable Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers or Ditches may be made, and accordingly have them, cut with all convenient expedition, and Towns and Cities built upon them in ſuch manner, as the ſayd Rivers and Ditches may be brought through the ſaid Townes and Cities is ſundry Channells, and that as much as is poſſible there be an outlet from the ſayd Rivers or Ditches into the Sea.</p>
            <p>2. That without farther delay the Parliament order, and ſee it put in execution, that in all the Fenns already drained, or to be drained, there be no ſtragling Tenements or houſes for any perſons to live in, except for Husband-men, who are not to be farre from their work and Calling, but that there be Townes and Cities built at an indifferent diſtance, where Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all other Occupations are to reſide, and navigable Rivers and Ditches made from one to another, and ſo into the Sea, which may be done with ſo many, and ſuch great advantages, as no part of the United Provinces doe yet enjoy the like, and make thoſe Fenny Lands, which at preſent are unpeopled, and ſo little worth, become more fruitfull, more populous and rich, not onely than any part of <hi>England,</hi> but even of the whole World, as having the preheminence of being deſigned ſo from the firſt foundation and beginning.</p>
            <p>3. That the Parliament (before the Nurcery of Timber for building Ships be quite deſtroyed, whereof there wants but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, I mean neer the water ſide to be had at eaſie rates, it being almoſt thrice as dcare as it was about thirty yeares agoe) doe prohibit not onely the cutting downe of Timber for Shipping, but that none capable of becoming fit for Shipping be uſed for building Houſes (I mean about the walls) in any part of <hi>England;</hi> nor for firing, but where there is no poſſibility of having Sea-coale or Pit-coale at moderate rates; and that the Nation be put to ſeeke out and fetch from abroad all manner of Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to build Ships withall, before the day of our extremity, till which, if wee happen to deſerre it, we ſhall then in likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood not be able to attaine it, except by permiſſion of our emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:62329:7"/>
if not envying Neighbours, whoſe mercies wee may finde to be <hi>Amboyna</hi>- like cruelties, and ſo much worſe than their vaſſalage, by how much that People, though ſubject to Exciſe and Taxes, may be thought one of the happieſt through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the knowne world, in that they have not onely ſpeedier Juſtice, than elſewhere, amongſt themſelves; but are by their Powers, who finde the advancing Trade to be the onely true State Intereſt and Pollicy, protected from all Forraign Injuries, and enjoy a full liberty of Conſcience, and by the wiſe manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Overſeers, have ſuch accommodations and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of Trading provided for them to their hand, as that they ſcarce have a beggar amongſt them, and generally live ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably and contentedly, as no Nation does the like.</p>
            <p>4. That ſome courſe be taken whereby the Money ſtock of the Nation may be encreaſed to ſuch a plentifulneſſe, as that moneys may be had for all mens occaſions at foure or five in the hundred, according to the ſecurity to be given, which the Act lately come out for reducing Intereſt to ſix in the hundred cannot doe; ſince, (beſides the being compulſory, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps were in all caſes beſt to be forborne, except where one man injured another in perſon or eſtate): that Statute cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe the money ſtock of the Nation, but rather contrariwiſe, as occaſioning leſſe money to be had at Intereſt, and if the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king higher Intereſt were not puniſhable, Forraign Nations as they did before theſe troubles, would likely bring in Moneys to put out at Intereſt, and wee had better pay twelve or thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen in the hundred, as they doe in <hi>Turkey,</hi> if wee cannot get it cheaper, than be quite without it. Now the <hi>Hollanders</hi> can bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a while longer forbeare that benefit which they made in <hi>England</hi> by Intereſt, than this Nation can their Trade, which like water being once ſtopped in its uſuall courſe, makes its own way by another channell, and is not ſo eaſily brought back againe. Wherefore ſome other courſe muſt be faln upon, which hath power of multiplying the ſaid ſtock of the Nation, either effectively or virtually to all intents and purpoſes; ſeverall whereof are herein propounded, and have been upon other occaſion more largely inſiſted on, which had they been made uſe of, would long ſince have been ſuccesfull againſt all objections or oppoſitions.</p>
            <p>5. That the Fiſhing Trade be faln upon in earneſt what ever
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:62329:7"/>
it coſt, without which there can be no conſiderable nurcery or ſucceſſion of Marriners, nor the Trade of this Common-wealth become predominant, and if not predominant over others, muſt become ſubſervlent unto others.</p>
            <p>6. That withall poſſible conveniency wee enlarge our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Plantations, and get farther footing in <hi>Barbarie, Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> with other Countries whereſoever it may be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed. Not onely that wee may the better provide our ſelves of Canvas for Sailes, Maſts, Timber, with all other things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for Shipping within our own Dominions; but alſo in that a little ſpot of ground, as <hi>England</hi> is, with its Dominions, if it doe not enlarge them, in future generations, I feare me, will be found inconſiderable in reſpect of <hi>Spain, Portugall,</hi> the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces,</hi> or any other European Nation, which ſhall have arrived to, and be armed with ſive or ten times a greater ſtrength, power, and riches, either from their <hi>Aſian, African,</hi> or <hi>American</hi> Dominions.</p>
            <p>Pleaſe to prohibit the killing Lambs for ſome few yeares, untill Sheep become multiplyed to as great a number as ever: But if you deſire to recover the departing woollen Manifacture, or prevaile with the Remainder not to bid <hi>adiu,</hi> You muſt not onely prevent the exporting Wools out of <hi>England, Ireland,</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> but muſt neceſſarily finde means of compaſſing all the Woolls of <hi>Spain</hi> for ſome yeares together, whereby <hi>Germany, France, Italy,</hi> and the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> being diſappointed, not onely our own Run-awayes, but their reſpective Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors will be neceſſitat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to repaire for <hi>England</hi> to be ſet a worke.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſent, to appoint a certain number of Free Ports (that all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s may enjoy the like immunity ſo ſoon as it may be gran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d without leſſning the Publick Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue) ſuch as are moſt commodioully ſcituated for trading with Forraign Countries, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> more equally diſtributing all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Forraign Commod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ties throughout this Nation, as alſo for the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> and cheaper exporting the Manufactures and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluities of this Common wealth, that all Merchandize which ſhall be b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap> into any of them, and afterwards for want of a good M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>t againe exported, may be free from Cuſtome and Exci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>; A courſe which almoſt all Sea- Towns in <hi>Europe</hi> have more or leſſe made uſe of at ſome time or other, as no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:62329:8"/>
ſlight Stratagem to make them become populous, and for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niming themſelves with all manner of Commodities at eaſieſt rates, becauſe being once brought thither, Merchants will ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſell them at indifferent prices, than carry them to another place, with ſo much more charge, danger of the Seas, and loſſe of time.</p>
            <p>Let the Natives of any Forraign Country, who ſhall come to trade with us, be equally free, as to Taxes and ſuch like immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, with the Natives of this Common-wealth, which will of neceſſity induce them to take up their habitations amongſt us, who elſe cannot make ſuch benefit thereof, as otherwiſe they might; Now righteous gaines and profits are the Rule whch all wiſe men ſteer by, and the end at which they aym; and even ſuch Forraigners as ſhall reſolve to reſide and live a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, will get the advantage of the others that onely come to ſell their goods and return againe, who in ſuch caſes cannot take the beſt of the Market, neither to ſell their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, nor make returns: But if it be ſaid, that theſe n mble pated Forraigners will hereby eat, or work the Natives of this Common-wealth out of their Trades and Callings; I anſwer, that ſuch Forreigners can onely prejudice ſuch Natives as are negligent, leſſe induſtrious, or that uſe falſe arts in their wayes and Trades; For if the Natives be but equally ingenious and upright in their Trades and Dealings, they being verſed and ſetled therein already, will have the ſtart and advantage enough of any Forreigners that ſhall afterwards begin and fall into the ſame Trades: But if ſome Forreiners be more nimble, ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and induſtrious in their wayes of Trading, than generally the Natives of this Land; may it not be conſiſtent with, nay even a ſpeciall demonſtration of the Wiſdome of our Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours to encourage ſuch active ſpirited Forreigners to a coha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation with us, whom the Fiſhermen Manifactors and Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of Forreign Nations will certainly accompany, for all follow and depend upon the Merchant, whereby their offſpring in the next generation become Natives like our ſelves? And if by ſuch courſe any of the leſſe ingenious Natives of this Land happen to be outgone in their own Trades and Callings, let them apply themſelves unto ſome other which requires leſſe ingenuity and activenes, as they ought to have done at firſt; and will not the induſtry and ingenuity of ſuch Forreigners
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:62329:8"/>
be a good leſſon and example to us, and contribute much to the inriching and accomodating the whole Nation in generall?</p>
            <p>Bee pleaſed that ſecure Harbours and Ports be made in as many places as can poſſibly be round about <hi>England,</hi> and in each of them a ſtrong impregnable Caſtle that may command the Port or Harbour, and that in each of theſe Caſtles or Forts there be Store-houſes, with all manner of Proviſions and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition for ſhipping laid in at the cheapeſt rates, to furnlſh both the Common-wealths and all Merchants ſhips upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, but eſpecially in the Iſle of <hi>Wight</hi> and <hi>Harwich,</hi> or in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other place where the Common-wealths men of warre may ride or lye at Anchor ſecurely all the yeare long, and upon In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence of an Enemy upon our owne Coaſt or elſewhere, with all winds and weathers, from one ſafe Harbour or other, put forth to Sea, and get upon them before they be awares. Whereas at preſent our Enemies may (and 'tis poſſible we ſhall feel it hereafter more ſadly) every night in the yeare, If not even by day time, come aſhore almoſt round about the Coaſt, burne, fire, ſack, make our People captives, kill, with what elſe they pleaſe, and be gone againe, before their Countrey Neighbours which dwell ſo ſtragling, can come in to helpe them, or our men of War get out to Sea, to prevent it, or reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue them And that in all theſe places there be Docks for build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ships all the year long, &amp; that being built they may conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue there in a ſafe Harbour, until there be juſt occaſion to put to Sea; and that when cauſe requires, they may be found ready to put out to S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with all winds and weathers, &amp; being at Sea, have Proviſions &amp; Neceſſaries of al ſorts, ſent them from thence, both ſpeedier and cheaper; leaving nothing unattempted for ſecuring Ships riding at Anchor in the <hi>Downes,</hi> about <hi>Sandwich,</hi> or the Iſle of <hi>Tennet,</hi> where a ſecure Harbour would be more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous, then in any place of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Marriners</hi> be encouraged by certaine Immunities to take up their dwellings in the Iſle of <hi>Wight, Harwich,</hi> and in all ſuch places eſpecially where the Ships uſually Winter, or are u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually laid up in when they come from Sea, that they may be there in readineſſe when the Ships goe to Sea againe: by which courſe moſt of them may be diſcharged ſo ſoone as the Ships get in, and not need to be imbarked untill the Ships be ready to put to Sea, which will ſave ſome moneths pay unto them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:62329:9"/>
yearly; for the time which the States Ships ſpend in expecting Tide, Winde, and Weather, in getting up or downe the River of Thames, and out to Sea, and that ſo many thouſand Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men as the Common-wealth ſhall have need of, be kept in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall Pay all the year long, to be alwayes in readineſſe when they ſhall be called upon, and to have their Dyet over and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove when they are in Imployment; after which manner I believe the Common-wealth may be furniſhed at cheaper rates then at preſent, and Preſſing or compelling them prevented; which, whether for Sea, or Land-ſervice is a very great, if not the moſt eminent body of our former bondage, and next to the degree of Bond-ſlaves, lyable to be ſold in a Market, and no where in common practiſe throughout Chriſtendome, except in <hi>England.</hi> If You have money You cannot want men, and You may have money enough if You will Your ſelves make uſe of ſuch harmeleſſe wayes as have been propounded to You.</p>
            <p>Prevent the over-ballancing of Trade, Encourage the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation of Bullion and Forreigne Species of Moneys; and Regulate the Marchandizing Exchange, which becauſe they are the moſt myſterious parts of Trade, I ſhall crave leave to enlarge a little upon them.</p>
            <p>Moneys were invented to be a meaſure or price of all things, and to prevent the carrying up and downe more bulkie Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities to Barter or Exchange withall, which was firſt in uſe, and for that purpoſe moneyes were made of the ſcarceſt, ſineſt, and pureſt Mettall, that it might be ſo much more tranſporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to and fro.</p>
            <p>Then as the World went on more refining it ſelfe, Exchanges were found out, as well to prevent the exportation of moneys out of one Countrey into another, as alſo the danger and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſomeneſſe of carrying moneyes to and fro within each ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Countrey and Juriſdiction: upon which reſpect the moſt pollitick and expert Merchants in lieu of money ſend nothing but a ſmall piece of Paper, called <hi>A Bill of Exchange,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubſcribed by men of credit, is thought equivalent to ſo much money as the Bill of Exchange engages for. But where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Exchanges were eſpecially contrived to prevent the exporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of moneys out of one Countrey into another, through regardleſneſſe of our Magiſtrates, the ſaid Exchanges have been ſo Managed by the ſelfe-ſeeking Intereſt of particular Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:62329:9"/>
as did not only prevent the importing of <hi>Bullion,</hi> or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes into this Land, but neceſſitated the exportation of our moneyes, both Silver and Gold.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Moneyes are likely carryed out of England.</head>
               <item>I. Either becauſe there is more profit to be got by our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes abroad, then by remitting them by Exchange, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying them in Commodities. Or,</item>
               <item>II. Becauſe it may be moſt commodious for Travellers, or other Paſſengers to Carry them: Or,</item>
               <item>III. Becauſe ſuch paſſengers are ignorant both in Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and remitting or returning them by Exchange. But,</item>
               <item>IV. And eſpecially, becauſe all the Corn which is brought by Strangers, and all the Fiſh which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> take upon our Coaſt or elſewhere, and ſel in <hi>England,</hi> as at <hi>Yarmouth, Plymouth,</hi> &amp;c. are ſold for ready moneys, and thoſe moneys in likelihood all exported, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The gaine on tranſporting moneyes may proceed.</head>
               <item>1. Either becauſe our Commodities are growne dearer here in <hi>England</hi> to be bought. Or,</item>
               <item>2. Growne cheaper abroad in Forreigne Parts to be ſold. Or,</item>
               <item>3. Becauſe that they give more for our Moneys then the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecall value, to melt them in Forreigne mints, or make them currant in Payments above their value.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And all theſe three reſpects will vanquiſh if we can but keep our Trade in Ballance, or rather enlarge our Exportation of Commodities, above our Importation, and eſtabliſh the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change betweene us, and other Nations according to the <hi>Par.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The undervaluing our moneys by Exchange, the accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dating Paſſengers with moneyes whereever they goe, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire not to be troubled with Commodities though they might get ſomewhat by them, And the ſupplying their ignorance both in imploying, and returning them may be done by engaging all Merchants to obſerve the <hi>Par</hi> in their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:62329:10"/>
according to certaine Tables wherein the intrinſecall value of Forreigne Coynes in relation to ours is to be publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; and if this faile, it may infallibly be effected, by conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting a Publick Exchanger, or an Agent of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, who may be obliged to Furniſh all Paſſengers with the ful value of their moneys in moſt principall places where they goe, as likewiſe all Merchants with whatſoever Summes they deſire; in which caſe men will not hazard the danger of exporting their moneys, and if they doe and be diſcovered muſt be made to pay for it without remiſſion.</p>
            <p>And when this courſe is ſettled, then it is propounded, That all perſons be againe prohibited exportation of moneys; and that if the Captaine or Maſter, Maſters Mate, Purſer, Maſter Gunner, or Gunners Mate, or Boatſwayne doe contrive or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Exportation of moneys, or but know thereof, and doe not diſcover it, it ſhall be Confiſcation of the Ship, beſides double penalty to each of the parties ſo aſſiſting, or concealing; and that the accuſer or diſcoverer have one ½ of what is recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, provided it be within five years after the fact was done. Within which time if any of the parties ſhall accuſe the other, and make it appeare by one or two Witneſſes, or otherwiſe the accuſer for the firſt time ſhall not onely free himſelfe from any penalty, but enjoy one halfe as diſcoverer. And the having a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove ſuch a Summe of money aboard any Ship or Veſſel, ſo long time together, and in ſuch places, ſhall be underſtood a guilti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of an Exportation thereof. And if any other Marriner or perſon belonging to the Ship or Veſſel ſhall aſſiſt, or conceale the Exportation as above ſaid, ſuch Marriners or perſon ſhall forfeit all his Wages then due to him, and if he have none due, be Lyable to a Fine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for enabling the Publick Exchanger, or furniſhing the Common-wealths Agent with a ſtock of money and Credit, whereby he may furniſh all mens occaſions by Exchange, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Par,</hi> as aforeſaid: It is neceſſary that he have a Stock, and how that may be raiſed <hi>gratis</hi> hath been made out to ſeveral Worthy Members, and ſhal be further demonſtrated when required. Then,</p>
            <p>If the Common-wealth keep a Correſpondent, or Banker in <hi>Paris, Antwerp, Amſterdam, Roterdam,</hi> and in ſuch like princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal places of Trade, and have a ſtock of money, or Credit with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:62329:10"/>
each of them, their Publick Exchanger may eyther returne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys upon them, or receive Charges from them according to the <hi>Par.</hi> or intrinſecal value, which will hinder tranſportation, and this can be no dammage or loſſe unto the Parliament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their Agents deale onely according to the true worth of the Coynes in themſelves at the Mint, what ever the denomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations be, or however they be Lightned or Embaſed: &amp; beſides</p>
            <p>1. If all moneys Delivered or Received by Exchange, paſſe through this Publick Exchanger or Banckers hands, or be ordered to be paid in Bank, you may ſee who are Deliverers, and who Takers, and to and from what parts moneys are remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and received, and by whom: and by this Ballance of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changes you may ſee how the pulſe of the ballance of Trade beats, by whom, and from whence the Miſchiefes concerning the ſame proceed, and be enabled to redreſſe them.</p>
            <p>2. As by an exact rule in the <hi>Cuſtome-Houſe</hi> you may know what Goods each Forreigner Imports and Exports; ſo here you may ſee what moneys he remits, or receives and make a ballance; for Strangers may be thought to be the greateſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters of our moneys, and thoſe Sea-men, Cheifly dealing likewiſe much in Merchandiſe. Now til this be more fully made out by practiſe, it is humbly moved,</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That no <hi>Gold-Smith</hi> or other perſon upon great Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be ſuffer'd to melt any of the Common-wealths Coin.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> That no Gold and Silver Lace be made in <hi>England,</hi> but of ſuch Silver and Gold thred or Plate, as is imported, until we ſee the <hi>Bullion</hi> begin againe to be imported into <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That no moneys be permitted to be ſent into <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, New England, Barbadoes, New-found-Land,</hi> or any of our other Plantations, until <hi>Bullion</hi> begin to come in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> That all Gold and Silver Mines formerly diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red within this Land, may be now further ſearched into, and others more neerly ſought after, for ſupplying us with a Money Stock of our owne, until we can bring in one from abroad.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> That there be no pence nor halfe pence made of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, becauſe ſo ſubject to be worne out, broken, and quite loſt.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:62329:11"/>
                  <hi>Sixthly,</hi> That it be afreſh declared what Quantity of the Common-wealths Coyn, and how much Forreign Coyne every Ship may carry for her owne Store or Proviſion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all wants or accidents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and how they are to be furniſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> againſt all Immergent occaſions.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Be pleaſed to erect a Court of Merchants for the ſpeedy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining all Controverſies about buying and ſelling, or any other emergencies rela erect a Court of Merchants for the ſpeedy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining all Controverſies about buying and ſelling, or nay other emergencies relating to Trade and Navigation.</p>
            <p>That Bonds, Bills of Exchange, or other Bills of Debt, be made irrevocably aſſignable from one man to another, as often as the laſt Aſſigne ſhall pleaſe, together with the delivery of the ſayd Bonds or Bills of Debt, which will virtually multiply the ſtock of this Nation, as to trading to all intents and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, eſpecially if you can induce the People by advantages to a voluntary regiſtring thereof, for which purpoſe onely there is a ſhort Propoſall ready prepared to be produced upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
            <p>But above all other Engines or Inſtruments, the greateſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence is due unto a Banck, which hath a capacity of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible preventing the exportation of our own moneys, and neceſſitating the Importation of Bullion and Forreign Coines, it will prevent the paſſing of falſe or clipt money, with the weare and waſt of money by telling it; ſave all the time now ſpent in telling money; Over-rule the Merchandizing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, whereby the Merchants of this Nation have been meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cheated in all parts of the world, where exchanging by Bills of Exchange is practiced. It is this onely that can reduce and keepe the Grand Ballance of Trade in favour of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by preventing the Importation of a greater quantity of Forreign Commodities, than wee export of Native; It is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of multiplying the ſtock of the Nation, for as much as concernes trading <hi>in Infinitum:</hi> In breife, it is the <hi>Elixir</hi> or <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers</hi> Stone, to which all Nations, and every thing within thoſe Nations muſt be ſubſervient, either by faire meanes or by foule.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed to let the Bill for a Country Regiſter at laſt to paſſe, which hath been ſo many yeares preparing, and yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarded, no doubt by ſome private reſpects or Intereſts; I meane to paſſe in ſuch a manner, as that a man being to make a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe of Lands or Houſes, may in a quarter of an houre, and for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:62329:11"/>
a twelve-penny matter or thereabouts, ſee who is the true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietor thereof, and what Judgements, Mortgages, and other Incumbrances there are upon them; which with the voluntary Regiſtring of Bonds and Bills of debt, as aforeſais, will prevent three fourth parts of all Law-ſuites, that otherwiſe will hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, and ſhorten ſuch as ſhall be begun hereafter.</p>
            <p>But what is it I have with ſo much confidence affirmed? Is there ſo great complaint of the want of moneys, eſpecially at ſuch low Intereſt, as were requiſit to drive Trade withall? And will the aſſigning over Bonds and Bills of debt irrevocably, virtually multiply the ſtock of the Nation ſo much, or ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, as the innumerable Bonds and Bills ſo many ſeverall times turned or aſſigned over from one man to another amount un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to? And hath a Banck yet a farther capacity, even of encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it unto an Infinitie, as I may ſay, by multiplying it vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, as to trading compleat in all its dimentions and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſits, to whatſoever ſumme a Nation can poſſibly ſtand in need of, though it were to engroſſe and monopolize the whole Trade of the world unto themſelves, as much and as effectual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as if all the money of the world were <hi>effective</hi> brought into that one Nation? And is it poſſible that the numberleſſe Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites may thus eaſily be prevented, the Remainder ſhortned, and the unmercifull expenſivenes abated, and will we not make uſe thereof? Will ſuch eaſie and obvious meanes be ſtill reje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or not made uſe of for multiplying our money-ſtock, and for encreaſing Trade, which onely will, and without which nothing can revive and repaire this waſted Nation? I beſeech Your Honours to pardon this ſeeming familiar manner of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogating, uttered in much tendernes, and with all ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiveneſſe tendered to Your gracious cenſure and acceptance: and yet I may not, nor can I ſmoother how heavily and ſharply the Proceedings of the Courts of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and even that of Parliament pinches us Commoners, which will be eaſier dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and ſooner forgot, if it be remedied hereafter.</p>
            <p>Pleaſe to take into conſideration how all the remaining Fenns may be drained, and all Commons incloſed, which would produce a great encreaſe of all things that the Land brings forth, provided it be done with ſo large alotments unto all people that have any intereſt or preſent benefit thereby, as they may be gainers by ſuch encloſures, if they will be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:62329:12"/>Confirme the Lawes in being with a cleerer explanation of them, for encouragement of all new Inventions and Improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that each Improver and Inventor may know what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage he may expect, and how it is to be determined and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured unto him, without ſo much attendance and charge.</p>
            <p>Conſider whether it be according to the Law of God, or a well ordered Common-wealth, that the Creditors Children or Heires of Malefactors ſhould be puniſhed for the ſinnes of their Parents, Predeceſſors or Debitors, and how heavily this hath layn upon many well affected to the State within theſe eight yeares: If it be ſayd that this is done the rather to keepe people in obedience to the Lawes, and that many deſperate perſons, who regard not their own lives, have notwithſtanding for their wiſes and Childrens ſakes forborn to commit ſuch flagitious crimes, to prevent the ruin which would have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faln them alſo; I eaſily believe it, but doe not ſee how it can be lawfull, to doe the evill of puniſhing Children for their Fathers offences, that the good of reſtraining their Fathers from committing ſuch offences may be compaſſed thereby.</p>
            <p>Pleaſe to prohibit the no leſſe deluſive and irrationall (as wee ſtand perplexed between Common Law and Chauncerie) than unconſcionable way of penary Bonds and Mortgages, which though they alwayes finde favour at Common Law, yet a man alwayes looſes by them, and ſhall never have them made good in Chauncerie, no nor ſo much as his Intereſt, dammages, and full charges allowed him. And if an honeſt man that hath a Bond, with a double penalty, ſhall apply himſelfe firſt unto the Chauncerie, deſiring the Juſtice of that Court for his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and Intereſt onely, alledging that he is neceſſitated thereunto, and to become firſt Plaintiffe there, or els after ſo many expenſive termes at Common Law, to be made Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, and hung up by an Injunction upon formall Cavills and ſuggeſtions for ſeverall yeares together; ſome ſycophant or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about that Court might poſſibly put an evill Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon ſuch proceedings, and endeavour to have the Bill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed; whereas if it were admitted, it might likely come to a hearing, and be decreed in a yeare, in regard by this courſe the greateſt part of thoſe formal ſuggeſtions, which delay the Hearing are prevented; whereas if between Common Law and Chauncerie, two, three, foure yeares or more are ſpun out, if
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:62329:12"/>
the Creditor dyes his children or heires are leſſe able to carry on the ſuit, though it be upon a Bond ſigned and ſealed in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of a hundred witneſſes, yet if the Debtor have but the Impudence to deny the payment, the Heires muſt be put to prove it, and if they cannot tell the very perſon that payd the money, or if he be dead, for all that I can learn, it is in the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Judges to make them looſe their money; and if the debtor dye before the buſines come to be decreed, and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on gained, if he left a perſonall eſtate, that is generally in great part imbeaſled; If land, that is made appeare not lyable to pay debts; ſo gracious are our Lawes, and ſo favourable is the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of them to ſuch as ſtand in moſt need of being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leived, and inſtead of penalties in Bonds, if the time of payment be elapſed, declare the Intereſt to be due, or ſuch greater dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages as the Creditor ſhall make proofe of to have ſuffered for want of his moneys, beſides full coſts, if not double; and in ſtead of Mortgages that ſuch Lands be interiourly engaged for payment of Principall Intereſt or dammages and coſts as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, and ſo much thereof onely ſould as will ſatisfie the ſame.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed to Enact all Wills and Teſtaments to be Regiſtred in the Country Regiſter, within eight dayes after the deceaſe of the Teſtator, or that the Will be found or brought to light, and that no perſon be permitted to diſpoſe of, or ſo much as remove any goods of the Teſtators, untill the Will be Regiſtred and proved by the Country Magiſtrate, or ſuch other neereſt Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature, as this Supreme Court ſhall appoint for determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all other cauſes, which will much prevent the emba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelling of the eſtate to defraud juſt Creditors, and ſecure the Remainder to the Legatees and Heires.</p>
            <p>Pleaſe to enact that ſingle Bills once proved or acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, be as valid as Bonds, or any other Obligation, and that together with Bonds they may have preſent execution.</p>
            <p>That Merchants and Shop-Keepers Bookes of Account be of unqueſtionable credit for liquidating or cleering debts, being demanded within a certaine terme of yeares, as in Your Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes ſhall ſeeme convenient, unleſſe ſuch Merchant or Shop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper be proved a knave, or that ſtrong preſumption appeare of ſome miſtake in relation to the Account in queſtion.</p>
            <p>That no man be arreſted till after Judgement, unleſſe upon
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:62329:13"/>
cleere evidence of intended removall of his uſuall habitation, or concealment of his goods or perſon upon affidavit, and that ſuddenly upon a Judgement, even in that inſtant, execution be granted both againſt perſon and eſtate of what ſort ſo ever.</p>
            <p>That all deceitfulneſſe in Spinning, Carding, Weaving, Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, with all other frauds of what kinde ſoever, in any manner of Commodities or dealings, which are exceeding deſtructive to Trading, be enquired after, and prevented in the future.</p>
            <p>That all new Manufactures, Handicraft my ſteries and Trades, practiced in other parts, or els with greater facility or exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitnes, and not as yet brought into <hi>England,</hi> at leſt with its per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, as Dying of Blacks in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> Crimſons in <hi>Venice,</hi> Watering and Chambletting of Silkes equall to thoſe of <hi>Florence, Bononia, Lucca, Venice,</hi> and other parts of <hi>Italie;</hi> making all ſorts of Linnins, eſpecially for Sailes for Ships, and the like, which will yeeld large matter to work upon, and may be all ſafely and advantagiouſly undertaken with advice and direction of ſuch as are well verſed in all ſorts of Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Trading; and (if wee regard our own safety and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, both which are eaſieſt purchaſed by purchaſing of Trade) ought to be throughly purſued, though to loſſe at firſt; And there is ſcarce any Art, Manifacture, or Workmanſhip in any Forraign Country, which with Integrity and Induſtry of the Overſeers, may not in a ſhort time become <hi>Engliſh,</hi> in greater perfection and exquiſitneſſe, than in any other Country, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I doe not finde all theſe advantages which have been ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered to this Nation, diſcovered to any one, nor to all the Nations throughout the Univerſe, nor ſuch diligence ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly practiſed as might be, which will ſtill yeeld Imployment to all numbers of People, though they multiply beyond Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident or beliefe, provided they have but elbow-roome to dwell by one another.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed to Erect Lombards or Bancks of Lone for fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing all people with moneys at Intereſt upon pawnes, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall or Land ſecurity, at reaſonable rates, which will not onely encreaſe Trading exceedingly, but alſo be of very great accommodation unto all others of whatſoever profeſſion: and the ſame Banck to be obliged to furniſh all poore people that ſhall deſire it as 20.<hi rend="sup">s</hi> at one time upon pawne gratis, to be repayd at ſix moneths, or the pawnes to be ſould: and that the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:62329:13"/>
ſame Banck be alſo obliged to take off at certain reaſonable rates all ſuch Commodities as poore people ſhall finde remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon their hands, and through deadneſſe of trading can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not finde to ſell them off, whereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> buy themſelves victualls, and continue in their Callings, which being well managed by perſons well verſed in the prices of Commodities, with the ſeaſons when, and the places where to ſell them, may rather turne to the encreaſe than detriment of the ſayd Banck.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed to Erect a certain number of Work-houſes in all Cities and great Townes throughout the Nation, whereto, all People, whether men or women, boyes or girles that cannot provide better for themſelves, may have recourſe, and be ſet to worke, of one ſort or other, which perſons of the meaneſt capacity, may eaſily attain to, and performe, at ſuch uſuall wages, of ſome ſmall matter under that which People of the like profeſſions doe give unto their Journey-men or women, provided they doe the ſame worke, both for quantity and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, that they may live comfortably thereon, and lay up ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what by their frugality, as may furniſh Tooles, and purchaſe a ſtock to ſet up for themſelves afterwards: This will not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly keepe multitudes of People from ſtealing and other lewd courſes, but much encreaſe the Manufacture and Handicrafts workmanſhip of the Nation: Nay, how many hundreds, if not thouſands, would ſuch a courſe as this have ſaved, who within theſe ten yeares, have even been ſtarved to death, and meerly dyed of want, or grieſe at leaſt, becauſe they had but little meanes of reliefe, and in a continuall feare of wanting neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary food and rayment?</p>
            <p>Many of theſe Propoſalls which I have taken boldneſſe to make unto Your Honours, I know to be of very Publick and great concernment, but this as being an Act of Mercy, extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to very many, and they in greateſt extremity of want, I deeme to ſurpaſſe all the reſt, as more ſavouring of Humanity, and more approaching to the wayes of God himſelfe. This being once eſtabliſhed, who ever ſhall be found a begging, may be confined hither to be kept working a certain reaſonable terme for bare food and rayment: And though this may ſeeme to be matter of charge, and at leaſt muſt require a ſtock to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin withall, yet it is capable of being ſo managed and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, as had I but a leaſe of my life for five yeares, I would
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:62329:14"/>
not doubt, to have ſome ſuch work a foote, as beſides the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſe which I here hold out unto the needie of the Nation ſhould have been ſufficiently beneficiall to the undertaker and it might have been attempted long agoe, when I was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier to live to manage it, and joy in the ſucceſſe thereof, could I have attained to an equality of Juſtice, or ſo much favour as a per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> obnoxious to Delinquency hath had.</p>
            <p>This Work-houſe might likewiſe take care of all Children, boyes or girles which are found about the ſtreets, as alſo lame and blind people who are not able to helpe themſelves, which here, both according to their capacities and abilities, may be ſet awork; and every man or woman with one arme or leg, onely being kept at work, may earn ſo much as will maintaine them in a comfortable condition.</p>
            <p>Then I hope it will be found neceſſary to appoint certain Truſtees or Commiſſioners, of untainted Integrity, and free from Covetouſneſſe, who may have Power of taking into their protection and care, all Orphans and their Eſtates, to ſee the managing and Improving of them to the beſt advantage during their minority, and to be accountable to them when they come to yeares: Theſe are a People who cannot helpe themſelves, whereby not onely their eſtates oftentimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a prey to men of evill conſciences, but they themſelves, deſtitute of pious and diſcreet education, doe too too often miſcarry in their perſons.</p>
            <p>That Publick Schooles where there are none already be ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in all parts of <hi>England,</hi> with competent ſtipends to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny head-Maſters and under Uſhers as ſhall be requiſit in each place, to which all poore people may be free to ſend their Children, whether boyes or girles, to be taught <hi>gratis,</hi> both to write and reade at leaſt, and ſuch Youths as are deſigned by their friends to a courſe of learning, be there inſtructed untill they be ſit for the Univerſities, or any other kinde of Clerk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. And becauſe Divine Providence hath caſt our lot in an Iſland, which cannot ſubſiſt ſecurely without Commerce with other Nations, which muſt neceſſarily be carried on by Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and Seafaring men, who by their Profeſſions are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out to croſſe the Seas, and ſee the Wonders of the deepe: As alſo in that this Land is very ſubject to high Waters in all parts, as that there is no travelling about our juſt occaſions
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:62329:14"/>
without being endangered thereby; I ſhould propound Firſt, That in ſtead of putting Malefactors to their <hi>Clergie,</hi> they may learne to ſave their lives by ſwimming.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, That theſe Publick Schoolmaſters may be Ingaged to ſee all their Schollers learne to ſwimme, and that all others, Parents or Guardians, be obliged to teach their Children elſewhere to reade, write, and ſwimme, or to ſend them to theſe Free-Schooles to be taught: The benefit of Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and Reading, though it be not ſufficiently conſidered by all Parents, and many poore people have not accommodate op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, and competency of meanes to get their Children taught, yet generally it is underſtood to be a pretty portion for Children that have nothing elſe to truſt to, to reade and write in ſome pretty perfection, and therefore doe what they can to get their Children educated accordingly, but Free-Schooles are ſo rare throughout this Land, and Writing-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſo weake in their Frofeſſion, as moſt Children and Youths by this meanes come ſhort of that perfection which otherwiſe they might ataine to; And beſides, whereas if the Children of the poorer ſort be of any bigneſſe as to become ſerviceable to their Parents, they cannot well be ſpared all day long, which the Parents are forced not withſtanding to diſpence with, and children to ſpend between going ſo farre to Schoole, and returning, together with the eight houres which are uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſpent in the Schoole, the whole day; when as the Maſter of Uſher cannot attend or teach every individuall Scholler one whole houre in a day; Now if but one, two, or three houres a day were ſet them, I mean to each particular Scholler, and ſo ſome appoynted to come at one houre, and ſome at another, and the Maſter or Uſher to apply themſelves to each Scholler in particular when he comes, the Schoole being ſuppoſed to be neer, the Scholler might quickly be at home againe to conn his leſſon, or practice by himſelfe, untill he be aweary, I mean ſo long daily as ſhall be requiſit, and bring him to a competent perfection, as to Reading and Writing, and have the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the day to ſerve his poore Parent in, which will become as a Recreation to himſelfe: But as to this feat of ſwimming, that all youths ſhould be trained up to it, I know it is a new Propoſall or Novelty, however when well weighed, I doubt not but it will be well approved of; and being ſo eaſily attained,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:62329:15"/>
and of ſuch uſe, as that few men who have been good ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and made often Voyages either by Sea or Land, but firſt or laſt have not onely ſaved their own lives, and other men, perhaps more than once, but even the Ship with all her Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Paſſengers and goods, which many times are loſt by the marriners deſerting her through faint-heartedneſſe, becauſe they are not expert in ſwimming, and haſtily betaking them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the boate to get aſhoare, whereas if they tarryed aboard ſo long as the Ship could be kept above Water, they might poſſibly ſave the Ship and goods by pumping, and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at laſt by ſwimming, when there were no other reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. Which how true it is, is manifeſt by the often meeting Ships at Sea forſaken of their men upon ſpringing of a Leake, that within a few dayes, perhaps houres, muſt have ſunke for want of pumping, had they not been ſo mett withall and ſaved. And beſides, upon occaſion of each aproaching danger, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert Swimmers are leſſe perplexed, which may juſtly be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted a farre greater deliverance, than even from death it ſelfe by drowning.</p>
            <p>That Phyſicians and Chyrurgions be appointed in every County throughout the Nation, particularly to every pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable diviſion of this great Citie of <hi>London,</hi> at the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick charge, who may be obliged once a day to viſit and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter according to their reſpective Profeſſions, to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever in that Diviſion ſhall deſire it, without any other fee or conſideration, but what the State allowes them.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, that Hoſpitalls be erected, and endowed, in every County and proportionable Diviſion, to which it may be free for all poore people to repaire for taking Phyſicke, as well to prevent ſickneſſe before it comes, as when it hath ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed on them, at the ſole charge and attendance of the Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall.</p>
            <p>And now if any body of a <hi>Judas</hi>-like ſpirit or diſpoſition ſhall object, that I herein expreſſe my ſelfe a very unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſervant unto the Common-wealth, in tendering to Them ſuch chargeable Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, that ſince the greateſt part of this, or of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nation, are contented to be ſubject, poore, and labour all day long, that others may more ſecurely Command, be wich in the aboundance of the Creature, and live at eaſe;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:62329:15"/>
That ſuch, the Powers or Great Ones of a Nation, even in diſcretion to themſelves, can doe no leſſe, than contrive and caſt about, how ſuch Subjects, ſervants, and labourers of theirs, who after a ſenſe may be ſayd to be their very ſtrength and riches in the <hi>abſtract,</hi> be ſo provided for in all reſpects, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of ſickneſſe, which makes them ſo helpleſſe in themſelves, and againſt which their ſmall pittance of portion in this world cannot poſſibly make proviſion, as that they may the better be enabled, not onely to continue ſtrong in their ſubjection, ſerving and labouring for the Powers and Great Ones, but that they may live under, and goe thorough it chearfully, and be prevented as to all thoughts and contrivances of change and Innovation: And yet becauſe if all this were to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed without charge unto the State, the Nation might like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier enjoy the benefit thereof the ſooner; I may not longer forbeare to aſſert, and be engaged upon my life too, to make it out, if I were called thereto; That there is no one of theſe Propoſalls, nor all of them together, but may be made de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrable unto any ordinary capacity, and by this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth be eſtabliſhed and put in execution within a <hi>very very</hi> few yeares, without greater (and perhaps with leſſe) charge than they are at, at preſent, and free from all manner of danger and inconvenience whatſoever; And being once effected, not onely prevent ſo many of the Nation in their Importunities for a new Repreſentative; but both diſpoſe them to be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and put You into a capacity of reſigning freely that Authority wherewith You have been ſo long inveſted, with Safety and Honour to your ſelves, and thoſe that have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to You. All which is humbly ſubmitted to Your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours deepe Wiſdomes to be conſidered on before it be too late.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 9. line 35. add after is, no. p. 13. l. 22. r. then. p. 14. l. 32. r. in, p. 18. l. 5. r. emergent. p. 21. l. 28. r. embeſelling.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
